<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Slow TV on Sailing Silver Girl</title>
    <link>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/tags/slow-tv/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Slow TV on Sailing Silver Girl</description>
    
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</webMaster>
    <copyright>&amp;#169; Will Jessop. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 15:37:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://sailingsilvergirl.com/tags/slow-tv/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Slow TV, 30 minutes of sailing from Harlech to Pwllheli, North Wales</title>
      <link>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/posts/slow-tv-30-minutes-of-sailing-from-harlech-to-pwllheli/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 15:37:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</author>
      <guid>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/posts/slow-tv-30-minutes-of-sailing-from-harlech-to-pwllheli/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This video is the return leg of our two day trip to Harlech from Pwllheli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first day we sailed from Pwllheli in light winds, drifting in about 10 knots on the beam on the Genoa only as we were in no rush to get to Harlech. We anchored overnight with a really nice view of Harlech castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the way back was a fun sail, 15 gusting 20 apparent and hard on the wind. At one point our Raymarine Autohelm stopped working with a &amp;ldquo;No Pilot&amp;rdquo; error putting the boat hard to port and locking the rudder. Hitting &amp;ldquo;Standby&amp;rdquo; on the head unit did nothing and I had to go below to go below to turn off the autopilot completely, but not unfortunately until we&amp;rsquo;d already accidentally gybed. Luckily the boom was sheeted hard in so didn&amp;rsquo;t have far to go but it was a pretty bad experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apologies about the audio, I don&amp;rsquo;t have a muffler for my GoPro and so there was a lot of wind noise. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried hard to minimise it, but have dropped the audio volume as well to make it less intrusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4WyThOyyqAg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
