<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Sailing Silver Girl</title>
    <link>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Sailing Silver Girl</description>
    
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</webMaster>
    <copyright>&amp;#169; Will Jessop. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 12:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://sailingsilvergirl.com/posts/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About the sailing yacht Silver Girl</title>
      <link>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/about-silver-girl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</author>
      <guid>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/about-silver-girl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Silver Girl is an Oyster 435 made in 1990. She is a 43ft/13.1m Bermuda rigged sloop. She has a fin keel with a 2m draft, a skeg hung rudder and a centre cockpit. Beam is 4.2m. The engine is a Volvo Penta MD31A making about 62HP. Fuel tankage is 340l and water tankage over 700l. The air draft is 18.3m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;full&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;images/Silver%20Girl.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/Silver%20Girl.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Silver Girl at Port Pendennis marina in Falmouth&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Silver Girl at Port Pendennis marina in Falmouth, click for full size.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going up the mast</title>
      <link>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/posts/going-up-the-mast/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</author>
      <guid>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/posts/going-up-the-mast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I needed to go up the mast for a couple of reasons, firstly I&amp;rsquo;d not done a rig check since we bought the boat (there were just too many things on the TODO list that took prefefence) and I wanted to make sure that everything was as it should be, but also because the active radar target enhancer had blown off and was sitting at the bottom of the Bay of Biscay somewhere and I wanted to check to see what the state of the remaining bracket was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was up there I took a photo looking down at the deck. It&amp;rsquo;s not a view you get to see of your boat very often and it&amp;rsquo;s nice to get a different perspective. I was pretty worried about dropping my phone though, next time I&amp;rsquo;ll take the GoPro tied to something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;full&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;images/View%20from%20the%20top%20of%20the%20mast.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/View%20from%20the%20top%20of%20the%20mast.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Looking down at Silver Girl from from the top of the mast&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Looking down at Silver Girl from from the top of the mast, click for full size.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also took a photo looking back across the Llŷn Peninsula while I was up there, I believe one of the lumps in the background is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowdon&#34;&gt;Snowdon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;full&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;images/Snowdon%20from%20the%20top%20of%20the%20mast.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/Snowdon%20from%20the%20top%20of%20the%20mast.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;View of Snowden from the top of Silver Girl&amp;#39;s mast&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;View of Snowden from the top of Silver Girl&amp;rsquo;s mast, click for full size.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to the new Sailing Silver Girl blog!</title>
      <link>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/posts/welcome-to-our-new-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</author>
      <guid>https://sailingsilvergirl.com/posts/welcome-to-our-new-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-are-we&#34;&gt;Who are we?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We (Will, the author of this blog, his family and friends) are the owners of Silver Girl, a 43ft/13m Oyster 435 sailing yacht made in 1990. We bought her in October 2021 in Falmouth, UK and keep her in North Wales, UK. You can read more about Silver Girl on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sailingsilvergirl.com/about-silver-girl&#34;&gt;about&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are relatively new sailors having only started sailing yachts in 2017 and very infrequently even then. Silver Girl is our first boat (I will write about why we chose Silver Girl as our first boat in a later post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-do-we-hope-to-acheive-with-this-blog&#34;&gt;What do we hope to acheive with this blog?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we&amp;rsquo;re relatively inexperienced sailors there&amp;rsquo;s going to be a lot of experience and skill we need to gain to become safe and confident on the water and I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to document some of the journey on that path here. Our long-term goal is to sail across the Atlantic in a few years time (2025/6 perhaps), and from here the path looks difficult and long. Hopefully in a few years we will be able to look back to see how far we have come, and to see the obstacles we overcame together to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog isn&amp;rsquo;t just going to be about learning though, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to document the journeys we take, the places we go, and our experiences there. This will be in part so I can point family and friends at a single place to learn about what we&amp;rsquo;re doing, but also so that I can remember everything we&amp;rsquo;ve done over the coming years as my memory is terrible. Should there be any itinerant visitor to this site then it would be great if they can find something useful, entertaining or interesting here too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for checking out us out!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
